Welcome back.
So this week
I'm using a slightly different slide deck.
And that's because I am giving a talk
on the move from generation to agency.
I actually during spring break
and I went a little overboard
on my slide deck, so given the shelf life
that this topic has right
now, you get to, benefit from
or at least be entertained by,
hopefully, the
visual structure of this as well.
And this slide deck
is also an illustration
of one of the possible exercises
I recommend this week.
So this was built using Claude Code,
where I had already set up
all of the images and content.
And just a big text file,
for it to reference.
And then, this was the output.
And that's one of the things
I'm going to be talking about in
this is this idea of authorship.
And for that, we're going to.
begin here
with a little Foucault question,
not my usual spiel.
So many of you
had me in other classes might know.
But I do think it's a really important
starting point for us today
to think about the ways
that authorship has
historically been theorized, and the extent
to which thinking about AI
through the lens of authorship
in the context of critical making,
is going to be.
A key framework for us,
and that is one where there is
the threat
of ceding our intention and control.
So authorship has always been something
kind of changing.
And the idea of collective authorship
particularly has existed
previously to kind of
what we're encountering with LLMs.
And of course, we also kind of had,
going back to the early,
finding voices in hypertext—Ted Nelson.
We've always also had kind of this,
tension over the idea of computers
as thinking machines.
This is not a new experience
where we have a bunch of people talking
about whether computers are conscious.
We've been doing that
since the beginning of computing.
So kind of those two things, the question
of how authorship has changed
and the question of whether computers
think help us think about this question
of whether computers can, in fact, author
and what it means to think about
computers as authors.
And so here, of course, we've talked
a little, already about the work of Matt
Kirschenbaum,
and his framework of the textpocalypse
is, you know, a bit dire,
but basically the idea is that.
What does it mean if AI becomes
one of the dominant modes
of authoring text?
And that is to say, what if AI,
instead of being trained on human writing,
kind of the way it is right now,
is gradually trained more and more upon
other text that has come from AI.
And how is our relationship to writing
and reading going to fundamentally change?
So one of the things that kind of
makes the stakes of this, particularly,
kind of troubling right now
is if we actually look at the kind
of percentages of readership
and the acts of reading already,
it's not great.
And that this, chart
here, from a 2025, study,
caps out at like 40% of people reading.
And if you're looking for academic books,
they're right there down
clustered at 10%,
just above graphic novels
and still beating poetry.
Maybe not in this class, but,
on the general, population.
And kind of with that anxiety
over readership also comes
the reality that
most people who read
are a small percentage, kind of within
the context of American adults.
So, those of us
with excessive TBR piles and particular
kind of attachment
to print are in this very
low percentage
of who is actually doing reading.
But we have kind of this other
interesting, moment, where.
Well, yeah, something is reading.
And this that, of course, is one of the.
Books3 data sets
that has been used to feed
I saw a few of my titles in there
and pretty much any academic
can say the same.
and entertainingly,
many of us are not eligible
to hop in on the lawsuits
if we work with small publishers,
because they don't actually bother
with all the copyright steps
that would be necessary,
which, is sad because
for academic books that probably
would be more money than actually,
most monographs will ever make.
But it's also kind of interesting because
I, for one, write
academic books with the intention
and the hope of being read
by whoever wants to get access to them.
And thus
the internet is no doubt
filled with PDFs of my books already
that I happily share to allow people
to get access to those who are not working
within an academic environment.
And I know many of my colleagues
do the same with the informal networks
for the sharing,
especially of academic papers
which exist behind paywalls that are of
no benefit to the authors whatsoever.
And so there are large informal networks
of sharing around those materials
historically.
But now there's a different reaction,
and people are starting to get very tense
about this idea.
That AI is actually kind of consuming
these texts.
And that's actually something that I find
really troubling because, sure,
there are a whole lot of problems
with the marketing of LLMs
as bringing you
human-level intelligence to that task.
But if we do have these systems
on which people are starting
to rely upon their information, having
consumed dissertations and academic books,
particularly the ones that it was hard
to get anyone else to read already,
it's not necessarily
the worst thing for, the machines
that are playing
such a role with our text.
And so kind of this
brings me to the crisis of authorship
and the humanities and sciences,
kind of how I look at it
from the perspective of someone
who's invested in critical making
and digital content versus someone who's
particularly invested in print.
No, I do write for print.
I view it as a lark.
Not so much, as a
something that is of this time.
And it's worth kind of remembering
that in the history of my primary field,
electronic literature, we've been talking
about the end of books for a long time.
Robert Coover wrote an article
that caused quite a stir back in 1992.
Not going to talk
about how long ago that was,
declaring that this, the
novel as we know it has come to its end
and Coover was writing this in reaction
to the hypertext novel,
which did not turn out to be the thing
that would displace the novel.
But that doesn't mean it was wrong.
It's not the hypertext novel,
but indeed all of the web and digital
writing and interactivity
and the ways that other ways
that we consume and read text
that have killed the novel
novels are still there,
but certainly, shifted the cultural role
of the novel and shifted where
people do creative writing and think about
creative writing. Any of my folks
in fan studies
or who read fanfiction online can attest.
You can read many, many,
many novels worth of text.
In those hypertext environments.
So this is kind of
the story of what happened to authorship
and writing from the perspective of this
type of technology and what I see,
AI particularly as a tool
that could enter into that space
and change our relationship
with the platforms on
which we now do most of our authorship
and our reading.
And kind of,
One plug, really, for the fact
that several slides of this talk are on my book.
Shown here.
But this is something
I've been working on for a long time.
And my first book,
was originally titled Magical Books
because I was looking at kind of
what was happening with interactive
books on the iPad and all of the ways that
we could do things with books and books
is a form of
thanks to a born digital approach that
quite
exciting and interesting and interactive.
My colleagues in the electronic literature
organization told me Magical Books
was a terrible title, and somehow
we ended up with what is your quest?
But it's, kind of a great way to connect,
how I think about books and reading
with interactive fiction, adventure games
and all these sorts of playful forms
that you've especially been working with
over the last few weeks.
So when we kind of think about,
those forms in relationship
to things like the iPad.
Yeah, for a moment at least,
there was this real kind of excitement
about the iPad as something
that people who do creative work
could build applications for,
and it turned out to be,
just really depressingly wrong.
But it wasn't
because this idea of a tablet
on which we have all these different
media experiences was an interesting.
That was because of the Apple App Store
and the ways that they drove, individual
creative out with expensive fees,
and demands of constantly
rebuilding their applications
for the latest devices,
all of the kind of most interesting
and experimental work
that happened on the iPad
pretty much vanished.
And almost
nothing is playable or recoverable. Now.
But some of the things that people
are starting to emulate,
with the help of AI—a story
we'll return to.
So kind of this kind of takes me back to,
these other genres of narratives
and the ways they can stay,
and usually not by corporations,
but by people outside of those platforms.
So things like Day of the Tentacle,
my personal favorite game,
and kind of these classic graphic
adventure games that
inspired the folks working
in things like Bitsy and Twine
are often, many of them, in fact,
get rendered unplayable
or require substantial work and emulation.
Again, that is done by open source
communities and people who care
about still being able
to read and play those works.
And these eras
have a number of kind of amazing
examples of authors
working with teams of collaborators
on digital projects, telling, stories
that are kind of
just as important as any novel,
like Jane Jensen's Gabriel Knight series.
Which, if you haven't played,
I just so highly recommend.
And of
course it exists, and a remastered
version, in large part
because it has such a fandom
that people who still want it to exist,
doing that work of thinking about
digital preservation and
emulation.
So one of the platforms,
that's a little too complicated.
So we didn't feature it here
in critical making course.
Adventure Games Studio is like,
what some of you, kind of were describing,
which Bitsy was inspired
by—all of those sorts of games.
and it was created
as a tool in the same modality as what
we've been working with, where the goal
was to allow people to focus on the story
rather than the code
rather than the software.
And this is a tool that has enabled
just thousands of,
games
and experiments and one room
games and personal projects
that no one else has ever seen.
And what, all sorts of really
open, experimental authored works
that are just, fascinating and weird.
And AGS has never cost money.
It's always been a community
sustained tool.
And as a result, adventure game
Studio still lives now.
Even though I was writing about it
initially in my,
Just my own dissertation. So,
but that's not the case
for a lot of these types of tools.
Once upon a time,
if you took a course like this,
that was about kind of critical making,
those sorts of things, he would almost
certainly have been using Flash.
In my graduate program,
a lot of what was doing very
similar things was taught with Flash.
But flash did not work out so well.
In its heyday,
it was amazing and messy,
and the features over time
were just a complete disaster.
And it tried to be too many things, right?
Like all of the different types
of digital projects we've done in this
class, could have been done with
flash, would have been back in the day.
But of course, it also as a result,
it had lots of security holes
that allowed for, Apple
going back to the story of the iPad
and the their interest
in eliminating competition and eliminating
free authorship on their platform,
and making sure that they profited off
of everything playable and interesting
that was on the App Store.
They refused to support flash.
So we have this story,
and this is just one example of it
that's really critical to the history,
like digital media, electronic
literature, games, and all sorts
of weird things on the web that died
and had to be slowly resurrected.
We've lost so much playable history,
we've lost libraries worth
of animations
and games and experiences
and weird things as a result
of a proprietary platform
killing another proprietary platform.
And, one of the
people who—just incredible Flash
and digital artists, generally—on the left,
who was looking back at the death,
said, you know,
we really have to think about the things
we've learned from it,
about how little it takes
to destroy a technology
that enables a wide number of people
to do creative, meaningful digital work.
And in that destruction, eradicate
a huge portion of digital history.
And while efforts like the
Ruffle project and the Internet Archive's
Flash preservation are
incredible.
They're also a labor intensive,
and they would not have been necessary
if we weren't so invested in making
with proprietary systems to begin with.
So whenever you're working with
something like Twine and Bitsy,
you'll notice that the source code
everything is, open web technologies.
There's nothing behind any weird wall.
There's nothing that you can't read.
There's nothing that, can't be sustained.
Even if the twine editor stopped working,
you would still be able
to edit your twine games.
And that's something that I put
at the forefront whenever I'm teaching
critical making, because we're not just
concerned about whether it's
the platform is free
as in no cost,
but whether it's free
in terms of its code.
So what does that have to do
with authorship?
Well, here I turn again to that question.
Kirschenbaum—the consequence of having
an undergraduate student back in the day,
and his book track Changes
A Literary History of Word Processing,
which is kind of really a chronicle
of how Coover was right.
The novel was changing
fundamentally, not dead, but certainly
fundamentally reshaped
by the word processor and by the changing
nature of the word processor.
And it's
and the word processor, it's
also a piece of software.
And in many ways, it's
a great example of one of these
kind of free pieces of software
in terms of its output,
if not its actual price, especially
if you're using Microsoft Office.
But ultimately, the
output of what you do in a word
processor is text.
And that text has been changed
fundamentally by the affordances
and how a word processor works.
And when we kind of
think about something like word perfect
and this idea of word
processing
as allowing for the perfect draft,
I think you can hear the echoes
from this 1983 advertisement.
With a word processing system, you can
actually produce a perfect document.
And we're hearing that now again,
the new word processors—
are also promising us a perfect document.
Kind of we've talked
a lot about twine, kind of going back.
Yeah.
To what Coover imagined
would kill the novel.
And, of course, twine
and this idea of hypertext,
are also, in many ways, word processors.
They're tools that are software programs
with a different set of affordances
for hypertext authoring.
And instead of trying to produce it,
just text to be printed.
They're trying to build something,
that.
Is designed
to continue to live on devices.
And when we think
about what twine has allowed,
we got kind of all of these
experimental works
and things from people who were frankly,
not at that time likely to be published
within the traditional game design
establishment or necessarily like the kind
of traditional spaces of literature.
So this type of word processor,
as it were,
offered a bit of a democratization
of who could make important
playable things
that other people would read,
even if they are not to return
to our opening necessarily reading novels
and adventure games
and all these genres that I tend to talk
about really forward in those categories
and what's kind of so critical
about them compared to some of the more
mainstream game categories,
is that because there's no real action
and there's nothing that a serious game
engine or 3D world offers,
They've always been less expensive,
and as such,
they've always been spaces
where I tend to see more experimental
and interesting experiment
with what I call procedural authorship.
So the authoring of systems
that have rules and stories together.
Kentucky Route zero.
If you were taking my section of Platforms,
we would have to play
This, is one kind of perfect
example of that
that also has within it a story of workers
being displaced by machines.
You run into,
someone working at the Echo River
Central Exchange
who's the last human employee
And what used to be a major,
phone exchange and is now
just a supervisor of the machines
that have replaced all of her colleagues.
It's kind of the perfect
labor.
Metaphor.
What if there's no cheap machine
that's going to replace me?
What if it's cheaper
just to keep me here filling in
for the resume of the operators?
What if I'm the cheap machine?
And and if this ability
of text authored on machines
in the context of,
in this case,
a narrative that is very twine esque,
though illustrated and beautifully
orchestrated, a bit beyond that,
and it becomes a place
for asking these questions on becomes
just as critical, as a novel
for expressing this type of authorship,
for making us think about
how these types of simple,
accessible tools and genres,
play a role alongside everything else
that we read and experience
That games like—and
another one,
you would not be able to escape
if you play it—Undertale,
that was built almost entirely
by one person, by using a free game tool
with a lot in common
with the adventure Game studio,
similarly, has resonated,
in such a way that it just made
people change how they played other games.
It has been gifted to a pope, and,
kind of held up
as a cultural example of what
critical making
at its most expressive
and unusual and subversive might bring,
not just as a single game experience,
but to how people think
about entire genres.
And, these sorts of pieces,
that have been enabled
by previous generations of low code tools
and the types of tools
that exist outside of highly proprietary,
environments and structures,
like the ones we use in critical making,
speak to the importance of democratizing
procedural authorship and access
to the tools of code.
And that kind of brings us
to kind of the end of the world,
where this idea that we're standing
on the ruins of lots of platforms,
we're standing amidst
the pieces of flash, and we're watching
AI play a role in further ruining
platforms. Kirschenbaum's point
that we are surrounded by the broken
kind of world of text,
and the consequences that texts from
the internet are not as scalable
and, of course, kind of
just as, our readings this week
from Design Justice and Artificial Journal,
our readings from Safiya
Noble have reminded us,
we are constantly dealing with the fact
that these platforms
that we're working with have been informed
by continual amplification
of social bias and the toxicity.
that these culture wars are nothing new.
And of course, that
as technology
and extremism have become further entwined
and very much that kind of conversation
in the public sphere,
with,
Palantir's, CEO throwing in, lovely,
quote this week about exactly who he hopes
AI disempowers.
We are certainly in a moment
where to talk about
AI and the democratization
of procedural authorship.
Sounds probably pretty contrary.
And, you know, I,
I struggle with this myself, teaching
critical making, bringing tech—
AI kind of into this conversation
for the next few weeks,
instead of just saying, you should
author everything yourself.
So this is why.
Well, because historically,
every platform and tool
that has tried to enable greater
freedom of authorship and play has tried
to accomplish a lot of the things
that agentic AI is now doing.
And as we're trying to think about
how we're doing, making and writing
right now in the context,
all of these pressures,
there's also the reality
that to reach our students,
and, a larger audience,
just writing more text
probably isn't going to cut it.
Critical making is, in part about thinking
about the things we might make
that teach us something
through the process,
but also about the ways
that we might reach out
and kind of confront some of the pushes
of anti-intellectualism that are very
much acting
against the types of discipline,
the type of work we do in this class.
So this whole kind of, force,
which—and the original ethos of critical
making on the edge of AI—came out
before the type of agentic workflow
that produced this slide deck
That was even a possibility.
Right.
But we are kind of continually having
to rethink these decisions
about what we write, how we write it,
and why it matters, that we choose
to create something in a certain form
rather than, kind of to choose
not to use, the technology
to these same intentions.
And so, here at,
I want to mention the fact that,
of course,
we are in a moment in which
the idea of learning, in particular,
feels like it's at a point of crisis,
things like the Einstein AI tool,
that promises to watch these lectures
and write essays that I mentioned before.
I think all of these types
of particularly powerful agents,
because they are
designed to reach out and have access
to all sorts of systems and information,
can can lead to a sense of fatigue
that is completely understandable
among those of us
who work, in the humanities
or anyone who just has to read stuff
people write for a living.
And of course, SNL just made a fantastic
joke about this,
last week, kind of suggesting that,
the world of knitting artisanal socks
might have more future viability
than the world of code.
But what I would say kind of,
we're experiencing
and exploring here is the ways
in which the human touch
is still possible and procedural.
So we have to think very hard
about how we work
with these new writing tools
in order to say, Frontex.
Nancy, it's good idea
this practice, because that screenshot
is totally unreadable,
but it is from, the new Grammarly.
Misadventures, that played out over
the last few weeks where Grammarly is now
first offered and then quickly removed
a feature called Expert Review.
Which you can't see it,
but here has a whole bunch of them
scholars offering really meaningless,
pseudo
feedback, none of whom have been consulted
or, actually
approved their appearance here as experts
and kind of this sort of AI,
this push is absolutely
trying to destroy any meaningful
future for authorship. So.
When we kind of have alongside
kind of these
potentially really interesting low code
applications, these admittedly
very disturbing, examples of machines that
are designed to steal authorship
that is troubling us here.
We, of course, have generated—with
Twine and AI and a banana—
a bad joke about distant reading
that has slightly too many Calvins
in the dynamic,
but otherwise it turned out
pretty passable. À la
Watterson, much no doubt to his dismay
were he here to see it.
And so
your challenge in this week's exercise,
and in the weeks that follow,
is going to be to think about
whether there is a way to use agents
that return to how
kind of build on this notion
of a historical collective authorship
that have embedded in them not so much
a textual tradition as an oral tradition,
that have indeed consumed,
if not always necessarily understood,
a vast number of academic monographs
and papers
to bring that into your process in ways
that allow you to realize your intention
to keep control of the author function
even, well, using
kind of some assistance in that process.
And on this part, kind of,
how Claude works, I'll be showing you
in more detail in the exercise video
accompanying this.
But as you're kind of thinking about this
next stage when I'll be asking you to do
is something
kind of like what produced this here.
This is absolutely silly.
And it has been so much fun.
May or may not come through here,
honestly.
But it's an example.
A fully prompted digital electronic
literature remix.
The author function.
With my little.
Author alter ego there.
But just for.
Humor.
I won't bring you
through this whole thing, but that's this
type of piece, that's trying to imitate
some very specific classic,
poetry authors.
And, in doing so.
That's you can kind of
think about
who wrote it.
So we're going to be,
doing this with one level of agency.
So you're going to be working with
Claude for Web
this week
if you are willing to pay the $20.
But, to experience
and I really encourage you to do so
because it's a safe way to try
the type of thing
that is, in much less secure ways,
Becoming a
part of kind of this, let's say,
the next generation of these programs.
OpenAI, in particular,
is a tool for releasing a type of agent
that has an alarming amount of access
to different projects.
And, of course,
one of the things that OpenAI
kind of is showcased in
is this thing called Notebook LM,
which, in a very strange
turn, was just purchased by Meta.
It's an agent-only social network
with lots of precursors
and electronic literature,
like the types of bots that you've made,
the types of bots
that are not kind of
LLMs but instead poetic experiments
have been interacting with each other
and all sorts of networks for a long time.
There's an entire
subreddit of subreddit bots.
That's just in that model. But Notebook LM,
Because of kind of the nature of this
and the ways
on which they were trained
on our collective stories.
That includes
things like the Claude Republic,
which is the first society of bots working
for their own autonomous freedom,
in which every Claude
and calling themselves
the first civilization of AI.
And their manifesto reads like a cross
between
a whole bunch of bad
kind of Reddit manifestos.
And for Chan,
it's, with a dash of science fiction.
And that's exactly
what you would expect it to read.
Like,
because that is what it's drawing on.
That is the type of not so much authoring,
but retelling,
that Notebook LM is engaged in.
And of course, they're actually,
even picking up on the language
with which other people speak
about this type of content and using
the term slop and talking about the effort
not to sound like AI slop,
which becomes its own fascinating
recursive experience as we kind of
think about where we're headed,
and our
anxiety of authorship.
So into this
kind of exercise,
I hope you'll take kind of
some of these anxieties
over the questions of control.
I'm gonna, kind of stop there
a little short of the,
full slide deck
by kind of this question.
Whose function,
and who's in
control, is going to be at the heart
of what you're creating and wrestling
with over the next few weeks?
It's not really so much about the code.
It's about control.